[
  {
    "questionId": 404476,
    "chapterName": "LIVING WORLD",
    "topicName": "TAXONOMIC CATEGORIES",
    "question": "Assertion (A): Higher the taxonomic category, greater is the difficulty of determining the relationship to other taxa at the same level. <br> \nReason (R): The higher taxonomic categories are more exclusive and the lower taxonomic categories are more inclusive in nature.",
    "questionImage": "#",
    "option1": " Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option1Image": "#",
    "option2": " Both (A) & (R) are true but the (R) is not the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option2Image": "#",
    "option3": "(A) is true but (R) is false",
    "option3Image": "#",
    "option4": " Both (A) and (R) are false",
    "option4Image": "#",
    "solution": "<br>  Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A).",
    "solutionImage": "#",
    "correctOption": "1",
    "difficulty": "1",
    "questionType": 0,
    "usageHistory": true,
    "correctAttempt": "33.3333"
  },
  {
    "questionId": 404478,
    "chapterName": "LIVING WORLD",
    "topicName": "TAXONOMIC CATEGORIES",
    "question": "Assertion (A): Higher the taxonomic category, greater is the difficulty of determining the relationship to other taxa at the same level. <br> \nReason (R): Lower the taxa, more are the characteristics that the members within the taxon share.",
    "questionImage": "#",
    "option1": " Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option1Image": "#",
    "option2": " Both (A) & (R) are true but the (R) is not the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option2Image": "#",
    "option3": "(A) is true but (R) is false",
    "option3Image": "#",
    "option4": " Both (A) and (R) are false",
    "option4Image": "#",
    "solution": "<br>  Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A).",
    "solutionImage": "#",
    "correctOption": "1",
    "difficulty": "2",
    "questionType": 0,
    "usageHistory": true,
    "correctAttempt": "33.3333"
  },
  {
    "questionId": 404836,
    "chapterName": "BIOLOGICAL CLASSIFICATION",
    "topicName": "PROTISTA",
    "question": "Assertion (A): Contractile vacuole is absent in sporozoans. <br>\nReason (R): All the sporozoans are endoparasite.",
    "questionImage": "#",
    "option1": "Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option1Image": "#",
    "option2": "Both (A) & (R) are true but the (R) is not the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option2Image": "#",
    "option3": "(A) is true but (R) is false",
    "option3Image": "#",
    "option4": "Both (A) and (R) are false",
    "option4Image": "#",
    "solution": "<br> Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A).",
    "solutionImage": "#",
    "correctOption": "1",
    "difficulty": "2",
    "questionType": 0,
    "usageHistory": false,
    "correctAttempt": null
  },
  {
    "questionId": 404470,
    "chapterName": "LIVING WORLD",
    "topicName": "TAXONOMIC CATEGORIES",
    "question": " Assertion (A): Species are static units in classification. <br> \nReason (R): Species do not change with time.",
    "questionImage": "#",
    "option1": " Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option1Image": "#",
    "option2": " Both (A) & (R) are true but the (R) is not the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option2Image": "#",
    "option3": "(A) is true but (R) is false",
    "option3Image": "#",
    "option4": " Both (A) and (R) are false",
    "option4Image": "#",
    "solution": "<br>  Both (A) and (R) are false.",
    "solutionImage": "#",
    "correctOption": "4",
    "difficulty": "2",
    "questionType": 0,
    "usageHistory": false
  },
  {
    "questionId": 404804,
    "chapterName": "BIOLOGICAL CLASSIFICATION",
    "topicName": "PROTISTA",
    "question": "Assertion (A): The protozoans are belived to be primitive relatives of animals. <br>\nReason (R): Protozoans are heterotrophs and live as predators or parasites.",
    "questionImage": "#",
    "option1": "Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option1Image": "#",
    "option2": "Both (A) & (R) are true but the (R) is not the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option2Image": "#",
    "option3": "(A) is true but (R) is false",
    "option3Image": "#",
    "option4": "Both (A) and (R) are false",
    "option4Image": "#",
    "solution": "<br> Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A).",
    "solutionImage": "#",
    "correctOption": "1",
    "difficulty": "2",
    "questionType": 0,
    "usageHistory": false
  },
  {
    "questionId": 405645,
    "chapterName": "PHOTOSYNTHESIS IN HIGHER PLANTS",
    "topicName": "LIGHT PHASE",
    "question": "Assertion (A): Immediately after light becomes unavailable, the biosynthetic process continues for some time, and then stops. <Br> \nReason (R): The biosynthetic phase of photosynthesis depends on the products of the light reaction.",
    "questionImage": "#",
    "option1": "Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option1Image": "#",
    "option2": "Both (A) & (R) are true but the (R) is not the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option2Image": "#",
    "option3": "(A) is true but (R) is false",
    "option3Image": "#",
    "option4": "Both (A) and (R) are false",
    "option4Image": "#",
    "solution": "<Br> Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A).",
    "solutionImage": "#",
    "correctOption": "1",
    "difficulty": "3",
    "questionType": 0,
    "usageHistory": false
  },
  {
    "questionId": 405646,
    "chapterName": "RESPIRATION IN PLANTS",
    "topicName": "INTRODUCTION",
    "question": "Assertion (A): During oxidation of respiratory substrate energy does not release in a single step. <br> \nReason (R): Breakdown of respiratory substrate in single step leads to unfavourable changes in cell temperature.\n",
    "questionImage": "#",
    "option1": "Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option1Image": "#",
    "option2": " Both (A) & (R) are true but the (R) is not the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option2Image": "#",
    "option3": "(A) is true but (R) is false",
    "option3Image": "#",
    "option4": "Both (A) and (R) are false",
    "option4Image": "#",
    "solution": "<br> Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A).",
    "solutionImage": "#",
    "correctOption": "1",
    "difficulty": "3",
    "questionType": 0,
    "usageHistory": false
  },
  {
    "questionId": 405647,
    "chapterName": "RESPIRATION IN PLANTS",
    "topicName": "DO PLANTS BREATH",
    "question": "Assertion (A): For plant respiration there is no need of specialized respiratory organs. <br> \nReason (R): Plants donot show great demands for gaseous exchange.",
    "questionImage": "#",
    "option1": "Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option1Image": "#",
    "option2": " Both (A) & (R) are true but the (R) is not the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option2Image": "#",
    "option3": "(A) is true but (R) is false",
    "option3Image": "#",
    "option4": "Both (A) and (R) are false",
    "option4Image": "#",
    "solution": "<br> Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A).",
    "solutionImage": "#",
    "correctOption": "1",
    "difficulty": "3",
    "questionType": 0,
    "usageHistory": false
  },
  {
    "questionId": 405648,
    "chapterName": "RESPIRATION IN PLANTS",
    "topicName": "GLYCOLYSIS",
    "question": "Assertion (A): Glycolysis is the oxidative process, while there is not utilization of $\\mathrm{O}_2.$ <br> \nReason (R): In glycolysis two redox equivalents are removed in form of two hydrogen atoms.",
    "questionImage": "#",
    "option1": "Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option1Image": "#",
    "option2": " Both (A) & (R) are true but the (R) is not the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option2Image": "#",
    "option3": "(A) is true but (R) is false",
    "option3Image": "#",
    "option4": "Both (A) and (R) are false",
    "option4Image": "#",
    "solution": "<br> Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A).",
    "solutionImage": "#",
    "correctOption": "1",
    "difficulty": "3",
    "questionType": 0,
    "usageHistory": false
  },
  {
    "questionId": 405649,
    "chapterName": "RESPIRATION IN PLANTS",
    "topicName": "AEROBIC RESPIRATION",
    "question": "Assertion (A): For complete breakdown of respiratory substrate Krebs cycle is essential. <br>\nReason (R): Krebs cycle is associated with step wise removal of all the hydrogen and $CO_2$ molecules.",
    "questionImage": "#",
    "option1": "Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option1Image": "#",
    "option2": " Both (A) & (R) are true but the (R) is not the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option2Image": "#",
    "option3": "(A) is true but (R) is false",
    "option3Image": "#",
    "option4": "Both (A) and (R) are false",
    "option4Image": "#",
    "solution": "<br> Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A).",
    "solutionImage": "#",
    "correctOption": "1",
    "difficulty": "3",
    "questionType": 0,
    "usageHistory": false
  },
  {
    "questionId": 405650,
    "chapterName": "RESPIRATION IN PLANTS",
    "topicName": "FERMENTATION",
    "question": "Assertion (A): In Natural alcoholic drinks (beverages) alcohol level can never be exceed more than 13%. <br> \nReason (R): Beyond 13% alcohol concentration yeast poison themselves to death.",
    "questionImage": "#",
    "option1": "Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option1Image": "#",
    "option2": " Both (A) & (R) are true but the (R) is not the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option2Image": "#",
    "option3": "(A) is true but (R) is false",
    "option3Image": "#",
    "option4": "Both (A) and (R) are false",
    "option4Image": "#",
    "solution": "<br> Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A).",
    "solutionImage": "#",
    "correctOption": "1",
    "difficulty": "2",
    "questionType": 0,
    "usageHistory": false
  },
  {
    "questionId": 405651,
    "chapterName": "RESPIRATION IN PLANTS",
    "topicName": "AEROBIC RESPIRATION",
    "question": "Assertion (A): Removal of all hydrogen atoms from pyruvic acid is the crucial event in aerobic respiration. <br> \nReason (R): These removed hydrogens are actually the source of energy for ATP synthesis.",
    "questionImage": "#",
    "option1": "Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option1Image": "#",
    "option2": " Both (A) & (R) are true but the (R) is not the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option2Image": "#",
    "option3": "(A) is true but (R) is false",
    "option3Image": "#",
    "option4": "Both (A) and (R) are false",
    "option4Image": "#",
    "solution": "<br> Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A).",
    "solutionImage": "#",
    "correctOption": "1",
    "difficulty": "2",
    "questionType": 0,
    "usageHistory": false
  },
  {
    "questionId": 405652,
    "chapterName": "RESPIRATION IN PLANTS",
    "topicName": "AEROBIC RESPIRATION",
    "question": "Assertion (A): Ubiquinone is one of the important carrier of respiratory ETS. <br> \nReason (R): Ubiquinone helps in oxidation of both $\\mathrm{NADH}_2$ and $\\text{FADH}_2.$",
    "questionImage": "#",
    "option1": "Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option1Image": "#",
    "option2": " Both (A) & (R) are true but the (R) is not the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option2Image": "#",
    "option3": "(A) is true but (R) is false",
    "option3Image": "#",
    "option4": "Both (A) and (R) are false",
    "option4Image": "#",
    "solution": "<br> Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A).",
    "solutionImage": "#",
    "correctOption": "1",
    "difficulty": "2",
    "questionType": 0,
    "usageHistory": false
  },
  {
    "questionId": 405653,
    "chapterName": "RESPIRATION IN PLANTS",
    "topicName": "AEROBIC RESPIRATION",
    "question": "Assertion (A): Oxygen is vital for aerobic respiration. <br> \nReason (R): Oxygen drives whole process by removing hydrogen from the system.",
    "questionImage": "#",
    "option1": "Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option1Image": "#",
    "option2": " Both (A) & (R) are true but the (R) is not the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option2Image": "#",
    "option3": "(A) is true but (R) is false",
    "option3Image": "#",
    "option4": "Both (A) and (R) are false",
    "option4Image": "#",
    "solution": "<br> Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A).",
    "solutionImage": "#",
    "correctOption": "1",
    "difficulty": "3",
    "questionType": 0,
    "usageHistory": false
  },
  {
    "questionId": 405654,
    "chapterName": "RESPIRATION IN PLANTS",
    "topicName": "AEROBIC RESPIRATION",
    "question": "Assertion (A): In ETS of respiration, oxidation of one carrier and reduction of another carrier is essential. <br> \nReason (R): In respiratory ETS, energy of oxidation reduction utilized for production of proton gradient.",
    "questionImage": "#",
    "option1": "Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option1Image": "#",
    "option2": " Both (A) & (R) are true but the (R) is not the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option2Image": "#",
    "option3": "(A) is true but (R) is false",
    "option3Image": "#",
    "option4": "Both (A) and (R) are false",
    "option4Image": "#",
    "solution": "<br> Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A).",
    "solutionImage": "#",
    "correctOption": "1",
    "difficulty": "3",
    "questionType": 0,
    "usageHistory": false
  },
  {
    "questionId": 405655,
    "chapterName": "RESPIRATION IN PLANTS",
    "topicName": "AEROBIC RESPIRATION",
    "question": "Assertion (A): The passage of protons through complex-V is coupled to production of ATP. <br>\nReason (R): Passage of protons through complex-V is associated with breakdown of proton gradient which leads to release of energy for joining of ADP & Pi.",
    "questionImage": "#",
    "option1": "Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option1Image": "#",
    "option2": " Both (A) & (R) are true but the (R) is not the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option2Image": "#",
    "option3": "(A) is true but (R) is false",
    "option3Image": "#",
    "option4": "Both (A) and (R) are false",
    "option4Image": "#",
    "solution": "<br> Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A).",
    "solutionImage": "#",
    "correctOption": "1",
    "difficulty": "3",
    "questionType": 0,
    "usageHistory": false
  },
  {
    "questionId": 405656,
    "chapterName": "RESPIRATION IN PLANTS",
    "topicName": "GLYCOLYSIS",
    "question": "Assertion (A): Calculation of the net gain of ATP for every glucose molecule oxidized is practically possible. <br> \nReason (R): All the pathway work one after another and do not take place simultaneously.",
    "questionImage": "#",
    "option1": "Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option1Image": "#",
    "option2": " Both (A) & (R) are true but the (R) is not the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option2Image": "#",
    "option3": "(A) is true but (R) is false",
    "option3Image": "#",
    "option4": "Both (A) and (R) are false",
    "option4Image": "#",
    "solution": "<br> Both (A) and (R) are false.",
    "solutionImage": "#",
    "correctOption": "4",
    "difficulty": "3",
    "questionType": 0,
    "usageHistory": false
  },
  {
    "questionId": 405657,
    "chapterName": "RESPIRATION IN PLANTS",
    "topicName": "FERMENTATION",
    "question": "Assertion (A): During fermentation oxidation of NADH to $\\text{NAD}^+$ is comparatively slow process than aerobic respiration. <br> \nReason (R): NADH arise during fermentation do not enter in ETC, it is to reduce the pyruvate or aldehyde.",
    "questionImage": "#",
    "option1": "Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option1Image": "#",
    "option2": " Both (A) & (R) are true but the (R) is not the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option2Image": "#",
    "option3": "(A) is true but (R) is false",
    "option3Image": "#",
    "option4": "Both (A) and (R) are false",
    "option4Image": "#",
    "solution": "<br> Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A).",
    "solutionImage": "#",
    "correctOption": "1",
    "difficulty": "3",
    "questionType": 0,
    "usageHistory": false
  },
  {
    "questionId": 405658,
    "chapterName": "RESPIRATION IN PLANTS",
    "topicName": "INTRODUCTION",
    "question": "Assertion (A): It is better to consider the respiratory pathway as an amphibolic pathway rather than only as a catabolic one. <br> \nReason (R): Breaking down processes within the living organism is catabolism, and synthesis is anabolism.",
    "questionImage": "#",
    "option1": "Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option1Image": "#",
    "option2": " Both (A) & (R) are true but the (R) is not the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option2Image": "#",
    "option3": "(A) is true but (R) is false",
    "option3Image": "#",
    "option4": "Both (A) and (R) are false",
    "option4Image": "#",
    "solution": "<br>  Both (A) & (R) are true but the (R) is not the correct explanation of the (A).",
    "solutionImage": "#",
    "correctOption": "2",
    "difficulty": "3",
    "questionType": 0,
    "usageHistory": false
  },
  {
    "questionId": 405659,
    "chapterName": "RESPIRATION IN PLANTS",
    "topicName": "INTRODUCTION",
    "question": "Assertion (A): During oxidation within a cell, all the energy contained in into the cell, in a single step. <br> \nReason (R): The energy released by oxidation in respiration is not (or rather cannot be) used directly but is used to synthesise ATP.",
    "questionImage": "#",
    "option1": "Both (A) & (R) are true and the (R) is the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option1Image": "#",
    "option2": " Both (A) & (R) are true but the (R) is not the correct explanation of the (A)",
    "option2Image": "#",
    "option3": "(A) is true but (R) is false",
    "option3Image": "#",
    "option4": "Both (A) and (R) are false",
    "option4Image": "#",
    "solution": "<br> Both (A) and (R) are false.",
    "solutionImage": "#",
    "correctOption": "4",
    "difficulty": "3",
    "questionType": 0,
    "usageHistory": false
  }
]
